We are picking up here with דף מ"ה Daf Mem Heh and
we pick up with the bottom of דף מ"ד עמוד ב', Daf
Mem Dalet Amud Bet, it's two parts of the same chapter as
we'll see in a minute. We pick up with the two dots
about twenty lines from the from the bottom, twenty-five lines from the
bottom. מנין שכיפר לו וידויו? Minayin shekiper lo viduyo? How do you
know that Achan's confession atoned for him? תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מנין
שכיפר לו וידויו? Minayin shekiper lo viduyo? שנאמר Shenemar ויאמר לו יהושע
מה עכרתנו יעכרך השם ביום הזה. Vayomer lo Yehoshua ma achartanu ya'acharcha
Hashem bayom hazeh. היום הזה Hayom hazeh אתה עכור. ata achur. So
the דרש drash is, God shall curse you today, today you're cursed,
ואי אתה עכור לעולם הבא ve'i ata achur l'olam haba but for
the future not because you confessed. וכתיב Uchtiv and another verse that
proves this, ובני זרח זמרי ואיתן והימן וכלכל ודרדע, Uvnei Zerach Zimri
v'Eitan v'Heiman v'Calcol v'Dardah, וכולם חמישה. vechulam chamisha. So these are all
the five sons of זרח. Zerach. But we know that עכן Achan
was עכן בן זרח. Achan ben Zerach. So עכן Achan must have
been somewhere in this list. So we understand that זמרי Zimri is
a name for עכן. Achan. And they're all equal like ויהיו בני
יעקב שנים עשר. Vayihyu benei Yaakov shneim asar. You know, מה כולם
חמישה כולם חמישה לעולם הבא. ma kulam chamisha kulam chamisha l'olam haba.
They all equally get עולם הבא Olam Haba even עכן Achan is
going to get עולם הבא Olam Haba just like his brothers. Now
which one here is עכן? Achan? So כתיב זמרי וכתיב עכן. ktiv
Zimri vechtiv Achan. So רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. חד אמר Chad amar
עכן Achan שמו, shmo, his name was עכן, Achan, ולמה נקרא שמו
זמרי? velama nikra shmo Zimri? שעשה מעשה זמרי, she'asa ma'aseh Zimri, he
acted like זמרי. Zimri. I mean זמרי, Zimri, you know, fornicated or
whatever, but he did this terrible sin and it brought death to
the to the Jewish people.
וחד אמר Vechad amar זמרי Zimri שמו, shmo, his name was זמרי,
Zimri, ולמה נקרא שמו עכן? velama nikra shmo Achan? שהכין עוונותיהם של
ישראל, she'hichin avonoteihem shel Yisrael, that he was הכין. hichin. רש"י Rashi
says the word הכין. hichin. Where is רש"י? Rashi? Hold on... Where
is רש"י? Rashi? גלגל עליהם
פקודות עוונותיהם. gilgel aleihem pkudot avonoteihem.
Oh, כאכנא ke'achna like a serpent. He causes he causes them to
roll upon them. אם אינו יודע להתוודות Im eino yodei'a l'hitvadot if
he doesn't know how to do וידוי viduy you teach him the
right thing to say. And then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says he
can say, what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that he can sort
of say, what is it? If he knows that the עדים edim
were מזומן mezuman he could say, my death should be an atonement
for all my sins except for this because this I'm innocent of.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows him to say that. And the
רבנן Rabbanan say, no, we don't allow him to say that, then
everybody is going to want to say that. Now the interesting thing
is that, well, is that it sounds like, you know, the response
is funny because it sounds like, if only the people that really
were innocent would say it, we would allow it, but we don't
want the guilty people to say it. But like, you know, you
don't even want the innocent people to say it because even if
somehow this guy was innocent and בית דין Beis Din made a
mistake, you don't want to be able to be bringing that type
of a, you know, of
bad repute about the בית דין Beis Din to allow him to
basically announce that
בית דין Beis Din is unjustly killing him. So anyway, but that
seems to be what's behind what they said, but you know, they
didn't say it that way. They said, no, then even innocent even
guilty people will say it. You know there's a line that says
the, you know, the prisons are filled with innocent people. And now
everybody's innocent, you know? So, so apparently like, you know, if somebody's,
you know, speaking to a prisoner, you don't say like what did
you do? You say what did they put you in here for?
Anyway, so, so
the גמרא Gemara says ואי אחי אצמן? ve'i hachi atzman? All right,
so what? Says let everybody say it and exonerate themselves. Why should
that bother us if they don't want atonement? No, כדי שלא להוציא
לעז על בתי דינים. kedei shelo l'hotzi la'az al batei dinim.
So now the גמרא Gemara says explicitly, we don't want ill repute,
we don't want people to now think that the בתי דינים batei
dinim are
executing innocent people. ועל העדים V'al ha'edim and on the עדים. edim.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מעשה באדם אחד שיצא ליהרג. Ma'aseh b'adam echad
sheyatza l'ihareg. Somebody who was going out to be executed. אמר, Amar,
אם יש בי עוון זה, Im yesh bi avon zeh, if I
am guilty of this sin, לא תהא מיתתי כפרה לכל עוונותי. lo
tehei mitati kaparah l'chol avonotai. This death should not be an atonement
for any of my sins.
I don't want any atonement for any sin if I'm guilty. ואם
אין בי עוון זה V'im ein bi avon zeh and if I'm
innocent of this sin, תהא מיתתי כפרה לכל עוונותי, tehei mitati kaparah
l'chol avonotai, it should be an atonement, ובית דין וכל ישראל מנוקין
u'Veis Din vechol Yisrael menukin and
the בית דין Beis Din they're exonerated, they did, you know, they
did nothing wrong, I mean they only did what they could do,
והעדים veha'edim but the witnesses who are the ones to blame, לא
תהא להם מחילה לעולם, lo tehei lahem mechila l'olam, they should never
have atonement. So here, you know, he's not, you know, it sounds
like, you know, it's a great line. Of course once you learn
how to sound sincere, you know, the hardest thing is learning how
to sound sincere. So once you learn how to sound sincere, other
people could say the same line.
You could be fake honesty, take honesty.
Right, exactly. But, you know, but it sounds like the fact that
he's not blaming the בית דין, Beis Din, he's not saying, you
know, he's willing to to risk atonement for all of his sins
in order, you know, to be able to say this. So it
really like sounds like he was innocent. חשו חכמים לדבר זה chashu
chachamim l'davar zeh where וחשו חכמים בדבר. vechashu chachamim badavar.
When they heard this, אמרו להחזירו אי אפשר amru l'hachziro ee efshar
שכבר ניגזר גזירה. shekvar nigzar gzeira.
To reverse it we can't, the ruling has been given and without
any evidence, as we learned earlier, you can't reverse it. אלא ייהרג
Ela yeihareg he has to be executed, וקולו תלוי בצוואר עדים vekola
taluy betzavar edim
and let the witnesses sort of, you know, let the yoke be
on them. They'll have to deal with the with the punishment. Of
course once somebody does get certain words out, right, what are you
supposed to do? Right, I mean if he asked permission to say
this presumably we wouldn't have allowed it because even though he said
I exonerate the בית דין, Beit Din, right, it still looks bad
for the בית דין Beit Din that they've executed an innocent person.
So it seems like it's not like we would have allowed him
to say this, okay, but he did say it and now what
can we do? We maybe we are killing an innocent person but
what choice do we have?
So the גמרא Gemara says, you know, what you needed is you
needed a governor who could issue pardons. Anyway, okay, so, so the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא כל כמיניה? Pshita kol k'minei? Of course we
have to execute him. So he's not believed, like how could he
reverse it even if it sounds sincere? So לא צריכא דהדרי בהו
סהדי. Lo tzricha d'hadri behu sahadei. The witnesses retracted. So the גמרא
Gemara says כי הדרי בהו מאי הוי? Ki hadri behu mai hava?
So what, even if they've retracted? כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד,
Keivan shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid, you can't retract your testimony.
So, you know, so this shows like, you know, what really happens
if everything is clear that we did the wrong thing and we're
about to execute an innocent man. The עדים eidim have retracted, all
of the evidence makes it clear he's innocent, right? But there's no
technical way that we can that we can change things. So we're
like stuck and we have to follow procedure it sounds like. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא, Lo tzricha, but the גמרא Gemara
says wait wait wait, no no no, it would have been impossible
to have considered that we could have done something and then we
don't do anything, but it would have been impossible to have considered
that we would have done something דאף על גב דקא יהבי טעמא
למילתייהו. d'af al gav d'ka yahavi ta'ama l'milsaihu. They don't just retract,
but they actually give a reason and it seems very very, because
normally you retract you say why should we believe your retraction more
than your original thing? But all of the circumstantial evidence and the
reason that they gave or whatever makes it clear that they actually
did testify falsely. And nevertheless we have to follow procedure. And now
here it has the בסוגריים. b'sograyim. Yeah, כי הא מעשה דבייא מכסא.
ki hai ma'aseh d'Baya machsa.
Some have this in parentheses like the story with בייא Baya the
tax collector. So who is this story of בייא Baya the tax
collector? This whole רש״י Rashi on the left hand column tells over
a story. I don't know where רש״י Rashi got the story. It's
a little bit of it is in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, part two
of it is in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, part one is not. I'll
tell it to you very quickly. The story is there's this evil
tax collector and this big צדיק, tzaddik, and they both died on
the same day, and there was some big thing that everybody they
were taking out the bodies to be buried and then something they
had all run away because the גויים goyim were coming. The bodies
got mixed up and they buried the רשע rasha in the grave
of the צדיק tzaddik and the צדיק tzaddik in the grave of
the רשע. rasha. So the תלמיד talmid was very was... that's the
tax collector. So the תלמיד talmid would say what did my רבי
Rebbi do to deserve this terrible thing to be buried in the
grave of a רשע? rasha? So the רבי Rebbi appeared to him
at night and he explained to him, you know, yes as there
was this one חטא chet that I did and there was this
one great מצוה mitzvah that this tax collector did and that's why
we got this, but in the end I have the you know
it's great for me in עולם הבא Olam HaBa and it's terrible
for him in עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. Okay and he basically saw
the tax collector there in גיהנום Gehennom or whatever, that the door
of גיהנום Gehennom was revolving you know like you know the hinge
was on top of the tax collector. So he said how long
is the tax collector going to remain there? So he says he'll
remain there until שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach dies and takes
his place in גיהנום. Gehennom. So he said... so he said what
did שמעון בן שטח... Shimon ben Shatach... so the tax collector point
is really trivial to this story. What did שמעון בן שטח Shimon
ben Shatach do? Oh there were all these witches that he's not
doing anything about. This is going to feed into the next משנה.
Mishnah. So he went and he told שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben
Shatach, so שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach did this whole thing
what I'll wait till tomorrow to to go back and we'll see
it in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and I'll talk about it, about how
he managed to capture all these witches and then he hanged them
all. And then all of the relatives of the witches really hated
שמעון בן שטח. Shimon ben Shatach. So what did they do? They
hired false witnesses to come and to testify that שמעון בן שטח's
Shimon ben Shatach son had committed some type of a capital crime.
So they testified against him and they you know and they weren't
able to שלוג shlug up the witnesses and they were taking him
out to be executed and then the witnesses basically you know sort
of had remorse and they said no we were hired by the
relatives you know we're lying etcetera etcetera. And it was obviously evident
that they had been lying and at the end of the day
they didn't do anything and they executed שמעון בן שטח's Shimon ben
Shatach son. And so, so that's I
mean we'll talk about that more tomorrow when we have the whole
story. But anyway so that would be an example where they're not
just retracting their testimony, we actually really do believe that they lied
because of the other circumstantial evidence and nevertheless we have to go
through with the process. There's no formal way we can interrupt it
which is like I guess deeply disturbing but on the other hand
you understand like once you allow for that type of discretion what's
to prevent that discretion from being terribly abused? You know, so yeah.
Didn't we learn that somebody if he's being taken to be executed
one of the חכמים Chachamim or something can can say oh I
have evidence or I have some reason?
Yes, but
but evidence has to be some actual evidence, not just witnesses you
know retracting is not evidence and that's just completely inadmissible there. What's
that word for retracting your testimony? There's a word for this and
an English word, anyway whatever it is.
Yeah I guess like in the case of maybe you had brought
like receipts for the life being paid like I...
that would be interesting. Like if there were witnesses that they had
been hired to testify falsely. Right. That's an interesting thing. That might,
that might, yeah.
But, you know, it's always I find it's hard to reconcile or
ponder evidence here if you will until now that we're doing everything
to exonerate the guy. I know.
We're going to get something similar by the עדים זוממים Edim Zomemin
case, like, you know, two witnesses come and say ראובן Reuven killed
שמעון. Shimon. These say no, you couldn't have said that עמנו הייתם.
Imanu Heyitem. Two more witnesses say ראובן Reuven killed—no, you couldn't have
said that עמנו הייתם. Imanu Heyitem. Two more עמנו הייתם. Imanu Heyitem.
In the end, it turns out that these מזימים Mezimim basically must
have been having a party for a thousand people, all of them
all the witnesses, and we still believe the מזימים Mezimim because in
formal rules, we believe the מזימים, Mezimim, you know? So sometimes like,
you know, we go by these formal rules. It is hard to
understand, you know? In capital cases. In monetary cases, you can do
more like, you know, אין לדיין אלא מה שעיניו רואות. Ein L'dayan
Ela Mah She'einav Ro'ot. You can use much more circumstantial type of
stuff. Well, it's something we'll be continuing to go back to as
we continue the מסכת. Masekhet. Let's move on. היה רחוק מבית הסקילה
ארבע אמות Haya rachok mibeit haskila arba amot we saw this in
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, מפשיטין אותו בבגדיו, mafshitin oto bevigadav, איש מכסה אותו
מלפניו, ish mechase oto milfanav, ואישה מלפניו ומאחוריה, veisha milfanav umachoreha, דברי
רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you strip
him naked, except you cover the genital areas and the woman the
back, but still they're considered basically naked. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, וחכמים
vachachamim say, האיש נסקל ערום ואין האישה נסקל ערומה. haish niskal arom
ve'ein haisha niskal aruma. No, you only strip the man, you don't
strip the woman. They don't, you know, they don't disagree that you
cover the genital areas of the man. It doesn't mean more naked,
but they say as the woman you don't strip at all. Okay,
or maybe you put on some simple garment but you don't really,
you know, you don't you don't strip her even if you're going
to cover. Now, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. האיש מכסה אותו פרק אחד
מלפניו. Haish mechase oto perek echad milfanav. The man you just do
one like, you know, פרק perek is just like one expanse, like,
you know, one width. Or רש"י Rashi says it could mean a
piece of cloth. You have one cloth in front of him. והאישה
שני פרקים בין מלפניו בין מאחוריה. Vehaisha shnei prakim bein milfanav bein
machoreha. But the woman, you have two pieces of cloth. So this
seems to indicate, although I don't think רש"י Rashi says it explicitly,
that it would not just be the genital areas but also the
breasts. But I'm not sure what that would be behind her, right?
It would be tied on somehow, right?
Maybe. I'm not sure. Anyway, I don't know exactly what it would
be behind the woman. But anyway, this seems to be that. מפני,
Mipnei, or maybe it just means that, you know, just to cover
more skin even if it's not necessarily like, you know, one of
those areas. מפני שכולה ערווה, Mipnei shekula erva, דברי רבי יהודה, divrei
Rabbi Yehuda, which is like this, you know, every part of a
woman is ערווה. erva. You know, it invokes the thing of שער
באישה ערווה, sear be'isha erva, טפח באישה ערווה. tefach be'isha erva. Every
part of a woman's body is seductive and, you know, naked and,
you know, to men to evoke sexual lust. But of course, the
point is, then why strip her? So it's this weird, you know,
sort of thing. You're going to strip her, but still and then
cover as much as possible but not the entire just two expanses.
So it's like a very strange balancing act, yeah Jenna?
So they don't consider like a man's butt?
That is correct. That is correct. There is a whole discussion about
that in ברכות, Berachot, but basically the really only הלכה halacha that
is considered the only part of a body a male body that's
naked is the genitals. For a woman, it's actually there is a
distinction between, I don't want to get into this too much, but
between what I would call like objective ערווה erva and subjective. The
difference would be, can you say a ברכה, bracha, for example, if
it's exposed and nobody else is in the room? It's not about
what somebody else's sexual response to the body is. It's about objectively
whether it's considered nakedness or not. So in that case, the basic
point is it's really only the genital areas. It's not the buttocks,
it's not the breasts for man, you know, for whatever. It's really
just the genitals. But when you talk about the subjective aspect of
ערווה, erva, being a woman, you know, and a room with another
man, you know, whatever, this type of thing, men seeing her, that
obviously shifts the conversation.
Okay. So, yeah, very provocative here. Intellectually provocative. Anyway, for some other
talk. וחכמים אומרים האיש נסקל ערום ואין האישה נסקל ערומה. Vachachamim omrim
haish niskal arom ve'ein haisha niskal aruma.
Okay, no, you don't do this for a woman. מאי טעמא דרבנן?
Mai taama d'rabbanan? What's the reason? אמר קרא ורגמו אותו. Amar kra
veragmu oto. You shall stone him. מאי אותו? Mai oto? What does
it mean him? אילימא אותו ולא אותה? Ilima oto velo ota? Do
we only stone men and not women? והכתיב והוצאת את האיש ההוא
או את האישה ההיא. Vehachtiv vehotzeta et haish hahu o et haisha
hahi.
Man or woman, you're going to take them out and stone them.
אלא מאי אותו? Ela mai oto? אותו בלא כסותו. Oto belo ksuto.
Him, all you have is him. You don't have his garment. He's
totally he's naked.
ואותה... ve'ota... I
lost my place... הא אותה בכסותה. ha ota bichsuta. But when it's
her, then it's not just her. It's her with her garments on.
No, but the minimum garments on.
Maybe. Anyway, but that's the חכמים. Chachamim. רבי יהודה אומר אותו בלא
כסותו. Rabbi Yehuda omer oto belo ksuto. No,
אותו oto does mean just the person naked. Okay, that is what
it means. But it's not meant to mean male as opposed to
female. Okay. אותו בלא כסותו לא שנא איש ולא שנא אישה. Oto
belo ksuto lo shena ish velo shena isha. Regardless of man or
woman. Now, what's behind this debate? Okay, how do you read this
פסוק? pasuk? But what's behind how you read the פסוק? pasuk? So
it's very interesting. Normally we just think, oh, he reads it this
way, he reads it that way. It's a technical issue. But like,
what motivates one person to read it this way and the other
that way? So here's the גמרא, Gemara, I mean I'm saying this
is how תוספות Tosafot reads the גמרא, Gemara, not how רש"י Rashi
with the next line I'm about to read,
reveals. their worldview, as if you would, that informs how to read
a פסוק, pasuk, which maybe is like obvious, but it's sometimes so
never said in the גמרא Gemara that it's always interesting to see
when it's said explicitly. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא, L'meimra, the
fact that the rabbis are choosing to read it that way, that
you don't strip a woman, דרבנן חיישי להרהורא. de-rabbanan chaishi l'hirhura. The
rabbis are concerned for sexual thoughts. And they're going to therefore read
it that way, that you don't strip the woman. רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, ironically the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said כולו ערווה, kulo ervah,
לא חיישי להרהורא. lo chaishi l'hirhura. He's not as concerned for the
people around having sexual thoughts.
Not concerned with women having sexual thoughts about the men apparently, right?
Well, that's always true. That's a good point, but that should be
said. Right, the always, the assumption is men seeing a naked, you
know, some part of a woman's body and having sexual thoughts. The
גמרא Gemara never sort of is concerned about the reverse, absolutely. And
that should be said. Okay, it's also interesting that it's framing it
about הרהור hirhur and about like not the person's dignity. Okay, but
that's at least, maybe that's because of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda language
of כולו ערווה kulo ervah evokes that type of a concern. Okay,
so that's the way the גמרא Gemara is framing it. ואיפכא שמעינן
להו, ve-ipcha sham'inan lehu, but we—it seems that they hold the opposite.
דתנן d'tenan הכהן אוחז בבגדיה ha-kohen ochez b'v'gadeha אם נקרעו נקרעו ואם
נפרמו נפרמו, im nikre'u nikre'u v'im nifremu nifremu, the כהן kohen holds
the garments of the סוטה sotah and rents it, if they tear
they tear, if they shred they shred, עד שמגלה את לבה ad
she-megaleh es libah until it exposes her heart, you know, her breast.
וסותר את שערה ve-soiser es se'arah and does her hair. רבי יהודה
אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer אם היה לבה נאה לא היה מגלהו. im
hayah libah naveh lo hayah megalehu. No, if it was attractive, he
would not have exposed it. אם היה שערה נאה לא היה סותרו.
im hayah se'arah naveh lo hayah soisro. If her hair was attractive,
he would not have undone it. So he is concerned for הרהור
hirhur and here he is not. So what do you make of
that? אמר רבה Amar Rabbah התם היינו טעמא שמא תצא מבית דין
זכאית. hasam hainu ta'ama shema taitzei m'beis din zaka'ah. There
they were afraid that she will come out exonerated. ויתגרו בה פרחי
כהונה. v'yisgaru bah pirchei kehuna. And once they see her body or
hair, the—they'll lust after her, now she'll have to go around anyway,
you know, in public having been having had people, you know, seen
her stripped naked and so on. So there we have to protect
her dignity. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says here, as opposed
to there, as opposed to here she's going to be executed. Okay,
dignity. Not her dignity, right, you're right, I am modernizing it, thank
you.
Only if she's attractive.
Right, correct, you are absolutely correct. I did that whole apologetics in
my head without realizing it. Thank you for calling me on that.
It is not her dignity, it is men lusting after her and
what might come from that. Okay, thank you for that correction. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says והכא v'hacha here, המיתה ha-misah she's being
killed. So nothing is going to come from men having seen her
naked. So that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says his position. וכי
תימא אתי לאיגרויי באחריניתא. v'chi teima asi l'igruyi b'achrisah. Oh no, once
they see one woman that way, that'll lead them to lust after
other women, you know. So is that to be a concern in
our case? אמר רבה Amar Rabbah so רבה Rabbah says גמירי gemiri
no, we have a tradition אין יצר הרע שולט אלא במה
שעיניו רואות. ein yetzer hara shoilet ela b'mah she-einav ro'os. The יצר
הרע, yetzer hara, which here means the sexual—often the standard יצר הרע
yetzer hara means sexual drive, not always, but often. Okay, the יצר
הרע yetzer hara has no control except over what a person is
seeing. Person doesn't transfer like a lust for one person or for
one thing somebody sees into some other person. I don't know, we
could have an interesting discussion if that's true. Okay, but what I'd
like to know is, you know, but it's—but it's interesting because often
the גמרא's Gemara concerned that if a person, a man, sees something
that's sexually provocative, that will lead to him having like a seminal
emission at night, right? If a man sees animals copulating, it's not
just afraid that he's now going to go, you know, have sex
with the people that he sees or the animals that he sees,
it's that it will lead to sexual thoughts, which will lead to
seminal emission. But apparently here that's not enough of a concern for
us to change our procedure. It would only be a concern if
it actually translated into some action that he would like lust after
this woman and go ahead, you know, and act on it. Okay,
so that's interesting.
But does it translate into הלכות halachos about כל אשה ערווה? kol
isha ervah? You did hear it on the radio but you don't
see it, so it's not עיניו רואות. einav ro'os.
Yes, so some people actually do want to use that. But again,
the interesting thing as I said is that there's a type of
a—of a lust that just leads to הרהורים hirhurim that leads to
זרע לבטלה zera l'vatalah that doesn't get acted on in any other
way, that clearly the גמרא's Gemara concern, you know, could have been
concerned about here, right? And then there's the יצר הרע שולט, yetzer
hara shoilet, which is going to get you to act. And that's
this issue of אלא במה שעיניו רואות. ela b'mah she-einav ro'os. So
there is this type of a different. But you're also right about
the issue about not just the person you directly encounter, the idea
of visual, right? And you know, I mean, so obviously people who
can't see, obviously, you know, but the idea that—how powerful the visual
is for men and so on is also true here.
Like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right.
Yeah, so that's my example
of—of
men not, not concerned about women's thoughts.
Well, but lust transferring because that's the
story of—oh, that's a nice
story where רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, where
this guy leaves the בית דין beis din and goes home to
sit with his wife because this beautiful woman came to—yeah,
yeah, that was רבא ואביי, Rava v'Abaye, whatever, right. It was—whoa, that
actually is even a little bit more relevant because your case is...
Not that they take the lust that they were feeling for רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and transfer it to their husband, but that when
maybe, a little bit more, they're like still thinking about it. Yeah,
it's a little different, but that's more like yes, person, a man
got sexually excited and then he brought that home to his wife.
Right, you know, but maybe it still means יצר השולט Yeitzar Hasholet
in the sense of provoking somebody to sin, but still, it's a
good counter-example. All right, excellent. Anyway, moving on. All right, אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so that we've resolved it. דרבי יהודה דרבי יהודה קשיא?
דרבנן דרבנן לא קשיא? De'Rebbe Yehuda de'Rebbe Yehuda kashya? De'rabanan de'rabanan lo
kashya? What, only רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda the problem? דרבנן De'rabanan not
a problem? דרבי יהודה De'Rebbe Yehuda you resolved. Here he's not afraid
of being naked because she's he she's going to get executed and
the lust won't transfer, whatever it is. There where afraid because she
might because what will happen if she's exonerated. But how about the
rabbis? They reversed their position. They weren't afraid by the סוטה sotah
and they're afraid here. So גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא אלא אמר
רבא דרבי יהודה דרבי יהודה לא קשיא כדישנינן. lo kashya ella amar
Rava de'Rebbe Yehuda de'Rebbe Yehuda lo kashya kid'shaninan. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
isn't a problem
like we said. דרבנן דרבנן נמי לא קשיא אמר קרא De'rabanan de'rabanan
nami lo kashya amar kra the verse says וניוסרו כל הנשים ולא
תעשינה כזמתכנה. V'nivasseru kol hanashim v'lo taasena kizmizatchena. All the women will
take מוסר, mussar, they will not do like her fornicating. So, so
הכא אין לך ייסור גדול מזה. hacha ein lecha yissur gadol mizeh.
So so you know here so there the people learning their lesson
is that they see her stripped and whatever and we want her
to be, you know you know, to be shamed, a public shaming.
Again, maybe even if she's innocent we want it because of the
actions that led to this, the way at least we're seeing it,
we're blaming her for all of this. All right, so there we're
prepared. Here we don't need to. Even if there was an element
that people should and that's always the question, is the point of
the public execution you know that everybody else who survives should learn
and there should be a deterrent factor? So even if that's true,
there you're seeing somebody get executed, right? So therefore here you don't
need to have the public shaming to be the thing that teaches
the מוסר. mussar. The execution will teach the מוסר. mussar. What about
the man?
We'll get to that. וכי תימא ליעבד בתרתי? Vechi teima l'ebed betartei?
Okay, you know what, but two lessons is better than one. Okay,
you get executed and shamed and executed. Some people, it actually is
very true. Some people will be more concerned about the public shaming
than they actually will be with you know with the fact that
they would eventually have to be executed for their act. So why
not do it? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה אמר קרא ואהבת לרעך כמוך ברור לו מיתה יפה.
Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha amar kra v'ahavta lereacha kamocha
bor lo mita yafa.
No, no, no. Here we have to balance. There's an idea of
teaching everybody a lesson, but there's an idea of trying to be
and this is such a powerful, you know we're we're we're familiar,
a lot of us are familiar with this, that the גמרא Gemara
applies ואהבת לרעך כמוך v'ahavta lereacha kamocha to this question about choosing
the right type of death. But you know we should take a
moment to appreciate how beautiful and like, you know, profound that is.
Like here is somebody who's a sinner who is being executed for
their sin in this very thing that is about the evil that
they have done and the reason that in some level they don't
deserve to live anymore, I mean one thing or another, their death
has to be an atonement and we still are treating this person
so much as an equal and one of us that we have
to give them the same dignity that we would want and the
same care, you know, that we would want for ourselves in this
situation. I mean I think that that's profound. And therefore even though
there has to be an element of people learning a lesson, there
has to be an element of doing everything as right by this
person as possible up to the last moment. Okay, and therefore we
do not want to introduce any shaming component that's not absolutely necessary.
So that's why we don't strip. So now the question of course
is, so then why do you strip the man? Right?
It's almost like this could be you, right?
Like, I mean, I think that's true too, right? To be able
to employ your imagination to do the ואהבת לרעך כמוך v'ahavta lereacha
kamocha you have to be able to imagine yourself in that situation.
Right, and that's right, that's very powerful.
Okay, לימא דרב נחמן תנאי, leima de'Rav Nachman tanna'ei, now let's say
that the רב נחמן Rav Nachman is the debate of תנאים tanna'im
because because you know why is it that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
is not concerned with with stripping? Where is his ואהבת לרעך כמוך?
v'ahavta lereacha kamocha? So the גמרא Gemara says לא דכולי עלמא אית
להו דרב נחמן. lo dechulei alma is lehu de'Rav Nachman. Everybody agrees
with ואהבת לרעך כמוך. v'ahavta lereacha kamocha. והכא בהאי קמיפלגי. V'hacha behai
kamifligi.
Here's the debate. מר סבר בזיוני דאיניש עדיף ליה טפי מניחא דגופא
ומר סבר ניחא דגופא עדיף מבזיוני. Mar savar bizyoni de'inish adif leh
tfei minei nicha degufa umar savar nicha degufa adif mibizyonei. So one
holds when it comes to a man he would rather have be,
you know, it's more important not to be shamed than it is
to be like, you know,
physically pained. The assumption is that if a person has clothes on
thatll cause more pain in the execution. The body will rub up
against the clothes, some type of a thing. It'll be a more
painful execution. So one would prefer to preserve his dignity even if
it means more physical pain and the other would prefer to, you
know, the physical to protecting himself from discomfort or from pain even
if it means, right, we have to create a standard. So you
know, so basically, so the חכמים Chachamim say, but this also is
the difference between the... man and the woman, right? So the woman
according to the חכמים, Chachamim, we are, I mean you could also
say it's a פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says אותו Otso and
we have to do it naked and we'll just make a difference
for the woman, you don't have to justify that anymore. But what
can we do? The פסוק pasuk says it. But there's also a
sense like no. So for the man, the shame won't be as
much, so we want to strip him, so it'll be less physical
discomfort. But for the woman, right, is it more important to, you
know, to protect her from the shame, and here it deals with
shame and not with lust, right? Or is it more important in
order to prevent, you know, her, to prevent the discomfort? So the
חכמים Chachamim say the מיתה יפה misah yafa is to keep the
woman clothed, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the מיתה יפה misah
yafa is to actually strip her. That would cause less pain and
we're not afraid of the ביזיון bizayon for the reasons we said.
Okay, let's try to at least turn the page, let's see if
we can get the next דף daf a little bit quicker. בית
הסקילה היה גובה שתי קומות אחד מן העדים דוחפו על מתניו נהפך
על גביו דוחפו על מתניו. Beis hasekila hayah govah shtei komos echad
min ha'edim dochfo al masnav nehepach al gabav dochfo al masnav. We
read this from ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ואם מת בה יצא, ve'im mes bah
yatza, pushed down, if he flipped over, you'd get him the other
way, that he's on his back. If that killed him good, ואם
מת בה יצא, ve'im mes bah yatza, ואם לאו השני נוטל את
האבן ונותנה
על ליבו. ve'im lav hasheni notel es ha'even venosnah al libo. And
if not, now this is why I paused when I read the
line in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi because I didn't, the משנה Mishna actually,
and this doesn't mean it was the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi משנה, Mishna, I'll
remind you that the משנה Mishna printed in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was
not in the manuscript of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it was taken from
a different manuscript of the משנה. Mishna. But the משנה Mishna in
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi had עד Ed one would put on the stone
and if עד Ed one didn't do it, עד Ed two would
put on the stone. Our משנה Mishna just has, if the pushing,
which our משנה Mishna reads better, if the pushing of עד Ed
one didn't do it, then עד Ed two would put on the
stone. It only has one stone and it immediately goes to the
second, you understand? עד Ed one does one thing, pushes off. If
that doesn't do it, עד Ed two puts the stone, it doesn't
have עד Ed one doing the stone. Okay. ואם מת בה יצא,
ve'im mes bah yatza, if that killed him good. ואם לאו רגימתו
בכל ישראל, ve'im lav regimaso bechol Yisrael, everybody gets involved. שנאמר יד
העדים תהיה בו בראשונה להמיתו ויד כל העם באחרונה. shene'emar yad ha'edim
tihyeh bo barishona lehamiso veyad kol ha'am ba'achrona. So that משנה Mishna
reads better. Okay. תנא וכל שקומתו שלו הרי כאן שלש, Tana vechol
shekomaso shelo harei kan shalosh, three heights. ומי בעינן כולי האי, umi
bainan kulei hai, do we need that height? ורמינהי מה בור שהוא
כדי להמית עשרה טפחים, uramini mah bor shehu kedei lehamis asara tefachim,
a pit that can kill an ox or whatever, or even a
human,
is עשרה טפחים asara tefachim deep. So you don't need it to
be this high as we discussed, that could be sufficient but, you
know, or necessary but not sufficient, right? It could be that that
has the possibility of killing, but here you want to make sure.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה אמר קרא ואהבת לרעך כמוך ברור לו מיתה יפה. Amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar kra ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha beror
lo misah yafa. No,
we have to choose a good death. Why is this a good
death? So presumably that it'll either cause him quicker, to die quicker,
like it'll be, or it'll cause him to die more certainly. Okay.
רש״י Rashi says שימות מהר. sheyamus maher.
Maybe he could die with עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, but this way
it'll be faster. I would also say this way it'll be more
certain. Okay, I'm not sure the גמרא Gemara says that. אי הכי
נגבהיה טפי, ei hachi nigbahay tefay,
oh then let's make it real high, it'll, you know, death on
impact, right? He'll die immediately, no suffering. No. משום דמנוול, mishum deminuval,
then the body would get deformed and it would be, it would
be, you know, now does that mean that even for his sake,
he would not want his body to be so deformed, that we
don't want the body to become so disgusted and mistreated? But I
think keeping within the ואהבת לרעך כמוך, ve'ahavta lere'acha kamocha, presumably it's
saying no, even he would not. Even if it would, he would
die immediately, you know, he would not want it to be as,
you know, with the cost of his body completely shattering and splattering
all over the place. Okay. Lovely image. אחד מן העדים דוחפו. Echad
min ha'edim dochfo. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. מנין שבדחייה, minin shebidchiya, how
do you know you push over? תלמוד לומר ירה יירה talmud lomar
yaroh yerah by הר סיני, Har Sinai, which again, probably means shoot
arrows to kill him from a distance if somebody gets near הר
סיני, Har Sinai, but here it's meant push off the cliff. ומנין
שבסקילה, u'minin shebisekila, how do you know to stone? סקול יסקל. sakol
yisakel. Again, actual סקילה sekila is mentioned where it speaks about the
death penalty, but here we're putting it within the הר סיני Har
Sinai in order to also to get in the pushing down.
Okay, I shouldn't say cliff, pushing off of the whatever, the platform.
ומנין שבסקילה ובדחייה, u'minin shebisekila uvidchiya, how do you know that you
would combine the two if necessary? תלמוד לומר סקול יסקל או ירה
יירה. talmud lomar sakol yisakel o yaroh yerah. I don't know how
the או o means and, I'm not going to worry about this.
ומנין שאם מת בדחייה יצא, u'minin she'im mes bidchiya yatza, how do
you know you don't need both? תלמוד לומר או ירה יירה, talmud
lomar o yaroh yerah, either. Of course it doesn't tell you how
do you know you start with the pushing off as opposed to
starting with the stoning, which would have been more the logical. The
very fact that we're bringing in the pushing off and making it
first just shows how we want to, like I said, reduce the
violence and also the sort of, you know, free-for-all-ness nature of the
act. ומנין שאף לדורות כן, u'minin she'af ledoros kein, how do you
know what you did by הר סיני Har Sinai you do in
future generations? תלמוד לומר סקול יסקל, talmud lomar sakol yisakel, the י׳
yud in the future, future oriented. All right, let's go a little
bit further, okay, I know it's 8:30, but we'll go a little
bit further. ואם לאו השני נוטל את האבן. ve'im lav hasheni notel
es ha'even. If not the second עד Ed would take the stone.
So the משנה Mishna just sounds like you place the stone on,
which is not going to be that effective. I mean, it might
be, but it would also be slow and excruciating. So נוטל, notel,
he takes it by himself. והתניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, vehatanya
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, אבן היתה שם משוי שני בני אדם.
even hayesa sham masui shenei benei adam. It was... so you needed
two people to lift it. One person couldn't lift it. נוטל ונותן
עליה, Noteil venosein aleiha, he would take it and put it on
the heart. So ואם מת יצא, V'im meis yatza, and then—and if
so, then עדיף, adif, and otherwise he gets the other people involved.
So anyway two people are required. ולטעמיך תשכח היא גופא, U'letameich tishkach
hi gufah, one minute! Why ask me that—that the Mishnah says one
and that says two. That source itself says both two and one.
First it says משאוי שני בני אדם, masoy shenei bnei adam, it
takes two people to lift it. And then it says נוטלה notlah
ונותנה על לבו. venosnah al libbo.
So does it take one person or does it take two people?
אלא דמדלו ליה בהדי חבריה, Ella demadlu lei bahadei chavreih, you get
two people to lift it up, so and then once it's off
the ground, one person holds onto it, ושדי ליה איהו, veshadei lei
ihu, and then one person throws it down by himself, כי היכי
דתיתי מזייר, ki heichi detisei mizayar, in order that it should go
fast. Because obviously one person can cast something down with more velocity
and strength than two people throwing it down. So first of all,
what's powerful about this is you don't just place it on his
heart, right? You lift up the stone and you throw it down
on him. That's way closer to סקילה. skilah. It's a little more
violent of an image than the Mishnah. It'll do a better job
killing him quickly, but it's closer to a real stoning and it's
a big heavy stone and you get two people together and then
one person steps back and the other one throws it down. Okay.
ושדי ליה איהו כי היכי—okay, Veshadei lei ihu ki heichi so ואם
לאו רגמוהו כל ישראל, v'im lav regamuhu kol Yisrael, if not then
everybody joins in, but the guy's pretty much lying there already, so
again it's not that violent of chasing a person and so on.
I'm going to send you all out Shirley Jackson The Lottery. You
have to read, I'm going to quiz you on it tomorrow. Okay.
Also the clip from Monty Python's The Life of Brian, the stoning
scene.
I found out the passage from The Handmaid's Tale that talks about
that.
Oh, that's also that one! Right. Okay, we can all share our
passages. Okay, anyway. Okay. דתניא מעולם לא שנה בה אדם. Datanya me'olam
lo shanah bah adam. So
what do you mean if that didn't work, do it then everybody
joins in. Don't we have a ברייתא braita that says that you
never had to do a second stoning? It was—at most it just
required the עדים eidim to do the stoning, it never got to
the people. Notice again, right? Sort of like all these things that
are like problematic—עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachas, לא היה
ולא נברא. lo hayah velo nivra. So here even though we kept
on pushing off the people stoning as much as possible, but we
still had it there at the end as a possibility. So ברייתא
braita says: No, no, no, that never happened. It never got to
the fact that the people actually stoned. It was always ended by
the עדים. eidim. So הגמרא ha-gemara says: Why is it in the
Mishnah? So הגמרא ha-gemara says: מי קאמינא דעביד? Mi kamina de'avid? Who
said that it ever happened? דמיצריך קאמינא. De-mitzrich kamina. The Mishnah's talking
hypothetically. If the second עד eid wouldn't finish the job, the people
would chip in. Okay, but it never got to it. It never
got to the fact that everybody else was part of the process.
Okay. אמר מר אבן היתה. Amar mar even haytah. So it says
that there was a stone there,
okay? ותני ברייתא: Vetani braita: אחת אבן שנסקל בה, achat even sheniskal
bah, ואחת עץ שנתלה עליו, ve'achat eitz shenitlah alav,
ואחת סייף שנהרג בו, ve'achat sayif sheneherag bo, ואחת סודר שנחנק בו.
ve'achat sudar shenichnak bo. All of these instruments of
execution—the stone, the sword, or whatever the different type of מיתה misah
was—כולן נקברים עמו, kulan nikbarim imo, they would all be buried with
the person, which is actually an important part—important image, right? Like you
don't have it that this is this is the knife that we
keep on using to execute people. Like you sort of almost want
to erase the memory of the event as much as possible. Like
it was terrible, it had to be done, but it shouldn't be
who we are. You want to just bury the whole thing. So
you bury the instruments of the execution. So if that's true, why
did the ברייתא braita say that if the first עד eid didn't
finish the job, the other people would come and it sounds like
the other people would use the same stone, right? Because
it
says—what does it say?
Does the Mishnah say—it just says ורגמוהו כל ישראל. veragamuhu kol Yisrael.
Somehow we're
understanding—yeah it's not explicit in the Mishnah, but somehow we're understanding that
they would use the same stone and that bothers us because we
say here that you would bury the instruments of execution. Okay. So
it
says—oh no, the problem is רש"י Rashi says it's the language of
the ברייתא braita where it says אבן היתה שם, even haytah sham,
which says there was this big stone that took two people to
lift, right? So it's not the people, I'm sorry, I got confused.
It's not what happens if it went from the עדים eidim into
the people. Anyway we said it never went away from the עדים.
eidim. But it says like there was a big stone that would
be used to finish the job. Right? So it sounds like there
would be a regular big stone here that they would use to
finish the job, so then it sounds like okay and if they
used it then they would keep it there. That would be the
regular finishing stone. Oh, aren't you supposed to bury the instruments of
execution? So הגמרא ha-gemara says: לא צריכא דמתקני ומייתי אחריני חלופייהו. Lo
tzericha dematkeni umaysei achrinei chalufaihu.
No,
it doesn't mean the same stone. If we ever had to use
one we would bury it and then we'd replace it. There would
always be some stone there, not the same stone. Okay.
Okay. נקברים
עמו—now, Nikbarim imo literally buried with the person. והתניא אין נקברים עמו—they
Vehatanya ein nikbarim imo wouldn't be buried with him. אמר רב פפא:
Amar Rav Pappa: מאי עמו? Mai imo? What do you mean with
him? In his area, like within his four אמות, amot, it wouldn't
be put in the grave itself, which is also nice, right? You
don't want like this idea that he's
marked—I mean, we'll see later that there's a special area in the
cemetery for those that are executed by בית דין. Beit Din. But
still the idea that he takes, you know, the signs of his
execution with him into the grave, you know, no. It's like nearby.
It's not in the same grave. But it's also buried. I do
think that burial is a way like we want to bury the,
you know, the memory of it. Like we don't want that to
be there to identify, like, you know, the fact that, you know,
a symbol of the fact that we execute people. All right, so,
I guess we'll have to stop here, and we will pick up
tomorrow.